Frederick Locker-Lampson Correspondence
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Frederick Locker-Lampson Correspondence
1770-1897
1853-1885
OSB MSS 152
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
11.89
(33 boxes)
The Frederick Locker-Lampson Correspondence is a collection of over 2,000 letters, accompanied by a few manuscripts and family papers, consisting primarily of letters received by Frederick Locker-Lampson. In addition to substantial quantities of letters from members of his immediate and extended families, the collection contains letters from scores of English literary figures, including F.T. Palgrave, Simeon Solomon, James Gibbs, and Richard Garnett. Some of Locker-Lampson's better-known literary friends and colleagues, Including Lord Alfred Tennyson, Robert Browning, and Austin Dobson, are represented by single letters, although there are no substantive correspondences with them. The collection also contains correspondence pertaining to Frederick's father, Edward Hawke Locker, including letters to his wife written during his naval career, and letters from the Irish author John Wilson Croker.
Locker-Lampson, Frederick, 1821-1895
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Frederick Locker-Lampson Correspondence is a collection of over 2,000 letters, accompanied by a few manuscripts and family papers, consisting primarily of letters received by Frederick Locker-Lampson. In addition to substantial quantities of letters from members of his immediate and extended families, the collection contains letters from scores of English literary figures, including F.T. Palgrave, Simeon Solomon, James Gibbs, and Richard Garnett. Some of Locker-Lampson's better-known literary friends and colleagues, Including Lord Alfred Tennyson, Robert Browning, and Austin Dobson, are represented by single letters, although there are no substantive correspondences with them.
The collection also contains correspondence pertaining to Frederick's father, Edward Hawke Locker, including letters to his wife written during his naval career, and letters from the Irish author John Wilson Croker.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Bernard Quaritch, Ltd. on the James Osborn and Marie-Louise Osborn Fund, 1993.
Ex libris Jonathan Locker-Lampson. Formerly on deposit at the East Sussex Record Office Library, United Kingdom.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in the exact order in which it was received, which is the order followed by the Historical Manuscript Commission in their item-level volume and bundle list. To quote from their introduction: "The bulk of the papers listed here are mounted and bound in six large albums; the remaining (mainly later) papers are in a number of bundles. The contents of the albums were mounted by James Gibbs in an approximately chronological sequence, which has been preserved in the Contents list." With the exception of the physical re-housing of the material in boxes and folders, no further arrangement work has been done on this collection.
Researchers should note that this guide can be used only in conjunction with the List of Locker-Lampson Mss.; a copy is housed in Box 1 of this collection. A second copy has been cataloged as Osborn e18. To search for a particular correspondent or topic in that index, look in the alphabetical lists in Parts II and III of that work, note the volume, page and document (or bundle and document) numbers given in the entry, and match them to the volume/bundle and item number spans given for boxes in the listing below. Part I of the List is the item level contents list of the collection. Researchers should look through this as well to determine if there are other items of interest that were not included in the alphabetical index.
Frederick Locker-Lampson, 1821-1895
Frederick Locker-Lampson was born Frederick Locker at the Royal Naval Hospital in 1821, the third child of Edward Hawke Locker, the civil commissioner for the hospital. He was educated at several preparatory schools before becoming a junior clerk in a colonial broker's office in 1837. From 1841 to 1849 he held a series of offices with the Admiralty, including deputy reader and précis writer for Lord Haddington. He received a leave of absence for health reasons in May 1849, and began extensive travels in Europe.
On July 4,1850, Locker married Lady Charlotte Christian Bruce, a daughter of the Earl of Elgin and a friend of Queen Victoria. They had one daughter, Eleanor, who in 1878 married Lionel Tennyson, the son of the poet. Locker retired from government service, and despite his continued poor health was a member of several London clubs; his literary friends included Thackeray, Tennyson, Trollope, Kinglake, Lamartine, Lord Lytton, and George Eliot. He also collected fine and rare books, particularly Elizabethan imprints, Louis XVI furniture, and Chinese porcelain. The Lockers often summered at Frogmore House, one of the royal retreats.
In 1857 he published his first and only collection of original verse, London Lyrics, a ninety page volume that received several editions during his lifetime. Lyra elegantiarum, an anthology of occasional verse, appeared in 1867. Lady Charlotte Bruce Locker died in 1872, and in 1874 Locker married Hannah Jane Lampson, a children's author who was also the heiress of Sir Curtis Miranda Lampson of Rowfant, first baronet. The couple had four children, two sons and two daughters.
Locker published Patchwork, a collection of extracts he referred to as his "little Commonplace-Book," in 1879. His father-in-law died in 1885, and Locker took the name Lampson in order to inherit the family estates. Locker-Lampson settled at Rowfant, and in 1886 privately published The Rowfant Library, A Catalogue. Edited by Alfred W. Pollard and R. H. Lister, the catalogue described the books, manuscripts, autographs, and works of art owned by Locker-Lampson. In the same year, his son-in-law Lionel Tennyson died of jungle fever during his voyage home from India. Two years later, Eleanor Locker Tennyson married the literary critic and politician Augustine Birrell.
Frederick Locker-Lampson died at Rowfant on May 30th, 1895. A volume of memoirs and genealogical information, My Reminiscences, was published in 1896, edited by Augustine Birrell, who also compiled a list of Locker-Lampson's late additions to his library. The Rowfant Library itself was sold to an American bookdealer, almost certainly Robert Dodd, in 1905.
Authors, English -- 19th century -- Archives; English literature -- 19th century; Authors -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Browning, Robert, 1812-1889; Croker, John Wilson, 1780-1857; Dobson, Austin, 1840-1921; Garnett, Richard, 1835-1906; Gibbs, James, 1825-1886; Locker, Edward Hawke, 1777-1849; Locker-Lampson family; Locker-Lampson, Frederick, 1821-1895; Palgrave, Francis Turner, 1824-1897; Solomon, Simeon, 1840-1905; Tennyson, Alfred Tennyson, Baron, 1809-1892
- Volumes, 1770-1876; Series I; 9.59; (24 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  The original order has been retained. The material in Volumes I-V is in rough chronological order; the letters in Volume VI are in rough alphabetical order. Volumes I-III contain the papers of Edward Hawke Locker. Volumes IV and V contain the papers of Frederick Locker-Lampson. Volume VI holds "the remains of an autograph collection."
  - List of Locker-Lampson Mss. (Box 1)
  - Volume I, page 1, item i - Volume I, page 100, item i, 1780-1808 (Box 2, Folder 1-71)
  - Volume I, page 101, item i - Volume I, page 157, item i, 1808-1815 (Box 3, Folder 72-151)
  - Volume II, page 14, item i - Volume II, page 63, item ii, 1807-1815 (Box 4, Folder 152-230)
  - Volume II, page 64, item i - Volume II, page 103, item ii, 1815-1820 (Box 5, Folder 231-305)
  - Volume III, page 20, item i - Volume III, page 65, item ii, 1820-1826 (Box 6, Folder 306-384)
  - Volume III, page 66, item i - Volume III, page 102, item ii, 1827-1834 (Box 7, Folder 385-445)
  - Volume IV, page 1, item i - Volume IV, page 9, item xxxviii, 1841-1859 (Box 8, Folder 446-540)
  - Volume IV, page 10, item i - Volume IV, page 19, item xii, 1859-1863 (Box 9, Folder 541-636)
  - Volume IV, page 20, item i - Volume IV, page 29, item xxvi, 1862-1865 (Box 10, Folder 637-728)
  - Volume IV, page 30, item i - Volume IV, page 50, item xxii, 1865-1866 (Box 11, Folder 729-829)
  - Volume IV, page 51, item i - Volume IV, page 59, item xiii, 1866-1867 (Box 12, Folder 830-959)
  - Volume IV, page 60, item i - Volume IV, page 65, item xx, 1867 (Box 13, Folder 960-1034)
  - Volume IV, page 66, item i - Volume IV, page 85, item vii, 1867-1890 (Box 14, Folder 1035-1128)
  - Volume V, preliminary page - Volume V, page 26, item vi, 1868-1869 (Box 15, Folder 1129-1270)
  - Volume V, page 27, item i - Volume V, page 49, item ii, 1869-1870 (Box 16, Folder 1271-1410)
  - Volume V, page 51, item i - Volume V, page 82, item v, 1870-1871 (Box 17, Folder 1411-1550)
  - Volume V, page 83, item i - Volume V, page 110, item iv, 1871-1872 (Box 18, Folder 1551-1693)
  - Volume V, page 111, item i - Volume V, page 144, item vii, 1872-1873 (Box 19, Folder 1694-1834)
  - Volume V, page 145, item i - Volume V, page 171, item vi, 1873-1874 (Box 20, Folder 1835-1979)
  - Volume V, page 172, item i - Volume V, page 195, item v, 1874-1875 (Box 21, Folder 1980-2120)
  - Volume V, page 196, item i - Volume V, page 220, item iv, 1875-1876 (Box 22, Folder 2121-2260)
  - Volume V, page 221, item i - Volume V, page 232, item vii, 1876 (Box 23, Folder 2261-2323)
  - Volume VI, page 28, item i - Volume VI, page 85, item ii, 1770-1867 (Box 24, Folder 2324-2379)
- Bundles, 1847-1897; Series II; 2.3; (9 boxes)
  The received order has been retained. For further information, see List of Locker-Lampson Mss. in Box 1.
  - Bundle VII, preliminary pages - Bundle VII, item 109, 1886-1888 (Box 25, Folder 2380-2498)
  - Bundle VII, item 110 - Bundle VII, item 135, 1886-1887 (Box 26, Folder 2499-2524)
  - Bundle VIII, preliminary pages - Bundle VIII, item 33, 1874-1892 (Box 27, Folder 2525-2559)
  - Bundle IX, preliminary pages - Bundle IX, item 18, 1880-1885 (Box 28, Folder 2560-2580)
  - Bundle X, preliminary pages - Bundle X, item 19, 1881-1895 (Box 29, Folder 2581-2601)
  - Bundle XI, preliminary pages - Bundle XI, item 105, 1885 (Box 30, Folder 2602-2711)
  - Bundle XII, preliminary pages - Bundle XII, item 20, 1858-1887 (Box 31, Folder 2712-2732)
  - Bundle XIII, preliminary pages - Bundle XIII, item 24, 1880-1884 (Box 32, Folder 2733-2757)
  - Bundle XIV - Bundle XV, item 7, 1847-1897 (Box 33, Folder 2758-2768)